<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>0x7df</title><link href="http://0x7df.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://0x7df.github.io/feeds/physics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://0x7df.github.io/</id><updated>2015-05-17T14:53:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Thermal radiation, Kirchhoff's law, and black bodies (1/4)</title><link href="http://0x7df.github.io/thermal-radiation-kirchhoffs-law-and-black-bodies-14.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-17T14:53:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-05-17T14:53:00+01:00</updated><author><name>0x7df</name></author><id>tag:0x7df.github.io,2015-05-17:thermal-radiation-kirchhoffs-law-and-black-bodies-14.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Thermal radiation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Thermal imaging" src="https://0x7df.files.wordpress.com/2015/05/sts-3_infrared_on_reentry.jpg?w=127" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All matter continuously emits electromagnetic radiation as a consequence
of its temperature. This radiation is called &lt;strong&gt;thermal radiation&lt;/strong&gt; or
&lt;strong&gt;heat radiation&lt;/strong&gt; (although of course it isn't intrinsically different
from electromagnetic radiation generated by any other means). Thermal
radiation is what makes thermal imaging possible, and why hot embers
glow, etc. From our everyday experience and from experimentation we can
see that both the wavelength and intensity of radiation emitted depend
in some way on the temperature of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can understand a lot about the properties of thermal radiation from
thought experiments, in particular by considering a hollow enclosure of
any shape, whose walls are opaque to radiation and which are held
everywhere at a constant temperature. The inner surface emits thermal
radiation, and therefore the interior space is filled with a radiation
field. The walls also absorb radiation. If at a particular time a small
volume &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( dv\)&lt;/span&gt; of space around a point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( P\)&lt;/span&gt; contains an amount of radiation &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( Q\)&lt;/span&gt;,
then the quantity &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( Q/dv\)&lt;/span&gt; is called the &lt;strong&gt;energy
density&lt;/strong&gt; at point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( P\)&lt;/span&gt;. We can show that &lt;em&gt;the energy
density in a constant-temperature enclosure is independent of the nature
of the walls of the enclosure, and depends only on the temperature of
the walls&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, imagine two such containers, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( A\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( B\)&lt;/span&gt;,
with the same wall temperatures, but in which, for some
reason (e.g. the material of the walls perhaps) the energy density is
different. It is higher in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( B\)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="https://0x7df.files.wordpress.com/2015/05/two_cavities.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="two_cavities" src="https://0x7df.files.wordpress.com/2015/05/two_cavities.png?w=300" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then imagine we can bring the two enclosures together to form a single
enclosure - perhaps they each have at least one flat face of a given
shape and size, which we can match up, and then instantaneously remove
these walls so the two cavities are joined into one. If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( B\)&lt;/span&gt;
had the higher initial energy density, then the energ
density in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( A\)&lt;/span&gt; will begin to increase, and the energy
density in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( B\)&lt;/span&gt; will decrease. Correspondingly, the
walls of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( A\)&lt;/span&gt; will increase in temperature by
absorbing the excess radiation, and the walls of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( B\)&lt;/span&gt;
will cool. The result is that we are causing heat to flow from one body
to another at higher temperature without doing any work, which
contravenes the second law of thermodynamics. From this we can conclude
that, if the walls are at the same temperature, then the energy
densities must be the same, no matter what. Hence, the energy density in
each enclosure is dependent on only the wall temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result also applies to the energy density in any restricted range of
wavelengths,  between &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( \lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( \lambda
+ d\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;. If, when we first conjoin the two enclosures,
instead of simply removing the interior walls we replace them with a
screen that is transparent to radiation only in the wavelength range of
interest, then the situation is the same. Therefore not only must the
total energy density be the same in the two enclosures (if their wall
temperatures are the same), but the energy density in any given range of
wavelengths must also be the same; i.e. the energy in both enclosures
must have the same &lt;em&gt;spectrum&lt;/em&gt;. This spectrum is called the &lt;strong&gt;Planck
spectrum&lt;/strong&gt; or the &lt;strong&gt;black-body spectrum&lt;/strong&gt;, and is evidently a function
of temperature only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Kirchhoff's Law (1859)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For radiation of wavelengths between &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( \lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; and
&lt;span class="math"&gt;\( \lambda + d\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;, the &lt;strong&gt;absorptive power&lt;/strong&gt; (or
&lt;strong&gt;absorptivity&lt;/strong&gt;), &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( a_\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;, of a surface is
defined as the fraction of the energy incident on the surface that is
absorbed. The &lt;strong&gt;emissive power&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( e_\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;, is
the energy emitted per unit area per unit time (per unit wavelength);
such that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( e_\lambda d\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; is the energy
emitted per unit area per unit time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing this, we can determine that, if a new body is inserted into a
constant-temperature enclosure of the kind discussed earlier, then some
amount of radiation, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( dQ\)&lt;/span&gt;, will be incident on each
unit area in each unit time, and an amount &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( a_\lambda dQ\)&lt;/span&gt;
will be absorbed. Since the nature of the walls of the
outer container cannot have any effect on the density or spectrum of the
radiation inside the enclosure, then the body cannot either; it must be
in equilibrium and the emission per unit area per unit time -
&lt;span class="math"&gt;\( e_\lambda d\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; - must equate to the absorption.
Hence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ a_\lambda dQ = e_\lambda d\lambda $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ \frac{dQ}{d\lambda} = \frac{e_\lambda}{a_\lambda} $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( dQ\)&lt;/span&gt; depends only on the temperature, then
for a given temperature both sides of the above equation are equal to a
constant, whose value depends on the temperature and the wavelengths in
question, but not on the composition of the body. This is &lt;strong&gt;Kirchhoff's
law&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ratio of the emissive to absorptive power for radiation of a
given wavelength is the same for all bodies at the same temperature&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A way of clarifying this is to compare two different bodies, placed
separately in the interior. The body discussed above, has equilibrium
state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ a_\lambda dQ = e_\lambda d\lambda $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but if this is replaced with a different body having different surface
properties &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( a_\lambda'\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( e_\lambda'\)&lt;/span&gt;,
then the new equilibrium state is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ a_\lambda' dQ = e_\lambda' d\lambda $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ratios &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( a_\lambda/e_\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; and
&lt;span class="math"&gt;\( a_\lambda' / e_\lambda'\)&lt;/span&gt; must clearly be equal.
Alternatively, you can think of a body inside and therefore in
equilibrium with one enclosure, being instantaneously transferred to a
different enclosure at the same temperature, and arrive at the same
conclusion again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Black bodies and perfect radiators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting consequence of the fact that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ a_\lambda dQ = e_\lambda d\lambda $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is that a stronger absorber (larger &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( a_\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;) is
also a stronger emitter (larger &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( e_\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;), at a
given temperature and for a given wavelength of radiation. In fact a
perfect absorber, for which &lt;span class="math"&gt;\( a\lambda = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;, and
which we therefore refer to as a &lt;strong&gt;black body&lt;/strong&gt;, also radiates as
intensely as it's possible to do so under the given conditions; so it is
also sometimes called a &lt;strong&gt;full&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;perfect radiator&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hole in cavity as black body" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/ef/Hole_in_Cavity_as_Blackbody.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An enclosure with a small hole acts nearly as a block body, absorbing
radiation incident on it with a very small probability of escape (as
long as the walls absorb a non-zero fraction of the radiation incident
on them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A black body is a theoretical construct - a substance like
&lt;a href="https://paleotechnics.wordpress.com/2014/02/25/lampblack-what-it-is-and-what-its-good-for/"&gt;lamp black&lt;/a&gt;
is an excellent but not perfect absorber - but one way to approach a
black body very nearly, is by constructing a sealed enclosure with only
a small hole through the walls. Radiation incident on this hole has a
very tiny probability of escaping again (i.e. by being reflected off the
interior walls) as long as the hole is small in comparison with the
dimensions of the enclosure; therefore this system acts as a perfect
absorber or black body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, such an enclosure doesn't have the characteristics of a
black body only in terms of its ability to &lt;em&gt;absorb&lt;/em&gt; the radiation
incident on it; radiation &lt;em&gt;emitted&lt;/em&gt; from the hole also has identical
characteristics to radiation emitted from a black body. We can see this
from the fact that, if we were to place a black body of the same
temperature into the interior of the cavity, then for it to remain at
this original temperature (which it must), the radiation emitted from
the cavity walls must be incident on the black body inside it with just
the same rate as the rate at which the black body is emitting radiation
itself. Hence, the radiation in the enclosure - or any enclosure with
constant wall temperature - is black-body radiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the radiation in the interior of any constant-temperature
enclosure has the intensity of black-body radiation, then another way of
expressing Kirchhoff's law is that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ratio of the emissive power of a body to the emissive power of a
black body at the same temperature is equal to the absorptive power of
the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Recall that the absorptive power is just a number between 0 and 1).
This ratio is also called the &lt;strong&gt;emissivity&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;absorptivity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    var location_protocol = (false) ? 'https' : document.location.protocol;
    if (location_protocol !== 'http' &amp;&amp; location_protocol !== 'https') location_protocol = 'https:';
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = location_protocol + '//cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="black body"></category><category term="thermal radiation"></category><category term="thermodynamics"></category></entry><entry><title>Restarting the LHC</title><link href="http://0x7df.github.io/restarting-the-lhc.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-22T18:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-22T18:13:00+00:00</updated><author><name>0x7df</name></author><id>tag:0x7df.github.io,2015-03-22:restarting-the-lhc.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[caption id="" align="alignleft" width="320"]&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/11304375@N07/2046228644/"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Large Hadron
Collider/ATLAS at CERN from Flickr via
Wylio" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2326/2046228644_05507000b3_z.jpg" title="'The Large Hadron Collider/ATLAS at CERN' by Image Editor, released on Flickr under the Creative Commons Attribution License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/), found via Wylio" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
© 2007 &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/11304375@N07/" title="'The Large Hadron Collider/ATLAS at CERN' published on Flickr by Image Editor"&gt;Image
Editor&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/11304375@N07/2046228644/" title="from Flickr"&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;
|
&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/" title="Creative Commons Attribution License  https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"&gt;CC-BY&lt;/a&gt;
| &lt;a href="https://www.wylio.com" title="Easily credit free 'large hadron collider' pictures with Wylio."&gt;via
Wylio&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the &lt;a href="http://home.web.cern.ch/topics/large-hadron-collider"&gt;Large Hadron Collider
(LHC)&lt;/a&gt; gears up,
after a big upgrade, to start its second major run, this post is a
reminder of the story so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Large Hadron Collider (LHC) is the largest &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Particle_accelerator"&gt;particle
accelerator&lt;/a&gt; in the
world, costing over 6.3b Euros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href="http://www.particleadventure.org/hadrons.html"&gt;hadrons&lt;/a&gt;, read
&lt;a href="http://education.jlab.org/glossary/proton.html"&gt;protons&lt;/a&gt;. (Protons are
one of a class of sub-atomic particles called hadrons; hence the name.)
The basic idea is to accelerate the protons until they have very high
energies, and then smack them into each other; the result of each
collision is the creation of a number other particles, which can be
studied. In particular, the purpose of it was to find and study one
particular particle called the &lt;a href="www.newscientist.com/topic/higgs-boson"&gt;Higgs
boson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How are the particles accelerated?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get to the necessary high energies, the protons need a long track; so
they're steered around a 27 km-long underground ring, typically
circulating many times before colliding. The acceleration, including the
steering round the circular track, is done by thousands of powerful
&lt;a href="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/solids/scmag.html"&gt;superconducting
magnets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How much energy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy of the protons being collided is measured in TeV -
tera-electron-volts (probably easier just to say teravolts - people will
know what you mean from the context). During the first run of LHC, up to
the end of 2012, the proton beams had an energy of 3.5 TeV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, 1 TeV is 10^12^ - or 1 trillion - electron-volts, where an
&lt;a href="http://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/23294/how-much-is-1-electron-volt-ev"&gt;electron-volt is defined as the amount of energy an electron would have
if it were accelerated from rest through a potential difference of 1
V&lt;/a&gt;.
That turns out to be 1.6 × 10^-19^ J, so 3.5 TeV is 5.6 × 10^-7^ J. For
context, a &lt;a href="www.thefreedictionary.com/joule"&gt;Joule&lt;/a&gt;is the energy it
takes to lift 100 g (e.g. a small apple) through 1 m at the earth's
surface; so, with an energy of 3.5 TeV each, it would take the combined
energy of only 1.8 million of these protons to lift that apple...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the upgrade, the proton energy will be 6.5 TeV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total collision energy is twice the beam energy, because two beams
of equal energy are directed head-on at each other. So the first run had
a collision energy of 7 TeV, and the post-upgrade second run will have a
collision energy of 13 TeV. The design intent was always that the LHC
would achieve 14 TeV, but because of technological problems (discussed
later), &lt;a href="home.web.cern.ch"&gt;CERN&lt;/a&gt;have played it safe and kept the energy
lower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even the lower collision energy of 7 TeV was a big step up from
what had been achieved before: the previous record, set by the 6.3 km
&lt;a href="http://www.fnal.gov/pub/tevatron/"&gt;Tevatron&lt;/a&gt;proton-&lt;a href="www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/28507/antiproton"&gt;antiproton&lt;/a&gt;
collider at &lt;a href="www.fnal.gov"&gt;Fermilab&lt;/a&gt;in Illinois, was 1.96 TeV. And, it
turned out OK, because as we'll see (and as you already know unless you
were living in a cave at the bottom of the sea in July 2012), the LHC
fulfilled its main purpose of discovering the Higgs boson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What are the limiting factors on collision energy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beam energy, and therefore the collision energy, is limited by the
&lt;a href="http://whatis.techtarget.com/definition/magnetic-field"&gt;magnetic field&lt;/a&gt;
that steers the beam, and the size of the ring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://physics.info/lorentz/"&gt;magnetic force&lt;/a&gt; provides the
&lt;a href="http://theory.uwinnipeg.ca/physics/circ/node6.html"&gt;centripetal
acceleration&lt;/a&gt;, so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ q_pvB = \frac{\gamma m_p v^2}{r} $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;~p~ and &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;~p~ are the charge and mass of the proton,
respectively, &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt; is its speed, &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; is the magnetic field strength, &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;
is the radius of the circular motion, and &lt;em&gt;γ&lt;/em&gt; is the &lt;a href="http://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorentz_factor"&gt;relativistic
factor&lt;/a&gt; that we must
include to account for the fact that the protons are moving at an
appreciable fraction of the speed of light. The energy of a relativistic
proton is &lt;em&gt;γm&lt;/em&gt;~p~, so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ q_p B = \frac{E v}{r} $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ E = \frac{q_p B r}{v} $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A larger ring would have a smaller radius of curvature, and so particles
could be given higher energies and still be kept on track with a given
field strength. For example, using the LHC-type 9
&lt;a href="http://www.teslasociety.com/teslaunit.htm"&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt; magnets in a 100
km-circumference collider, rather than a 27 km one, would allow an
increase of the collision energy to 50 TeV. Clearly, the limitation on
size is the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, for a fixed-size ring, further increasing the beam energy
means having to increase the field strength. The limiting factor for the
field strength is local heating in the superconducting coils, caused in
turn by movement due to the high fields themselves. The heating causes
the coils to cease to be superconducting; this is called &lt;em&gt;quenching&lt;/em&gt;.
The magnet starts to conduct normally, and releases a large part of its
stored energy as heat, which in turn boils off the &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2012/08/questions-and-answers-about-liquid-helium/"&gt;liquid
helium&lt;/a&gt;
coolant and induces high pressures. (Note that, during preparations,
quenching is done deliberately to increase the strength of the field
that the magnets can support. The field is gradually increased until
quenching occurs; when this process is repeated, the quenching occurs at
a higher field strength. This is continued until the magnets can support
a sufficiently high field for the beam energy required. The process is
called &lt;em&gt;training&lt;/em&gt;, and takes months.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, protons, like electrons and other charged particles, emit
&lt;a href="http://abyss.uoregon.edu/~js/glossary/synchrotron_radiation.html"&gt;synchrotron
radiation&lt;/a&gt;
and thus lose energy when they travel in circular orbits such as in the
LHC. The radiated power goes as the fourth power of &lt;em&gt;γ&lt;/em&gt;, and since the
energy of a relativistic proton is &lt;em&gt;γm&lt;/em&gt;~p~, the rate of energy loss is
proportional to the fourth power of the beam energy. Clearly also, the
loss is worse for electrons and positrons, because of their lower mass,
than for protons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is the beam energy all that matters?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other important aspect of a particle collider is the intensity of
the beam, which dictates the rate of collisions. This is usually
characterised by a quantity called the &lt;em&gt;luminosity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working out the collision rate is fairly simply. It helps to know that
the particles are actually grouped into &lt;em&gt;bunches&lt;/em&gt;, rather than being a
continuous stream. If we imagine one beam as a stationary target and the
other beam as impacting on it (with twice the nominal collision energy),
it makes it easier to work out the collision rate. The number of protons
in the target bunch is &lt;em&gt;n~T~&lt;/em&gt;, and the cross-sectional area of each
proton is &lt;em&gt;σ&lt;/em&gt;, so the total area 'blocked out' by the target protons in
&lt;em&gt;n~T~σ&lt;/em&gt;. The actual cross-sectional area of the beam is &lt;em&gt;πr&lt;/em&gt;^2^; so the
proportion of this that's blocked out by protons is &lt;em&gt;n~T~σ&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;πr&lt;/em&gt;^2^ -
the rest of the area is empty space. (This assumes that the protons in
the bunch are spaced out enough that, if we were to look along the
length of the 'target' beam, none of the protons further away from us
would be hidden behind any others. Because the size of the protons is so
astonishingly tiny relative to the cross-sectional area of the beam,
this is a fair assumption).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when the incident bunch of protons, &lt;em&gt;n~I~&lt;/em&gt;, impacts the target
bunch, the fraction of them that collide with a proton in the target is
equal to the fraction of the total area that's blocked out by target
protons; which we've already determined to be &lt;em&gt;n~T~σ&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;πr&lt;/em&gt;^2^. Hence
there are &lt;em&gt;n~I~n~T~σ&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;πr&lt;/em&gt;^2^ collisions for every bunch crossing. If
the rate of bunch crossings is &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;, then the overall collision rate is
&lt;em&gt;fn~I~n~T~σ&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;πr&lt;/em&gt;^2^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/ncomms/journal/v2/n9/full/ncomms1472.html"&gt;The cross-section for inelastic scatter is about 60
mb&lt;/a&gt;,
which is 6 × 10^-30^ m^2^. The diameter of the beam at the point of
collision is about 16 microns, so its cross-sectional area is 2 ×
10^-10^ m^2^. The ratio of these areas - and therefore the probability
of a collision - is about 3 × 10^-20^. The value of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is about 10^11^,
which suggests the number of collisions is 300 per bunch crossing. The
bunches are crossed every 50 ns, so there are 2 × 10^7^ crossings per
second, and so 6 billion collisions per second. (Actually, the figures
are about a factor of 15 too high - &lt;a href="http://cds.cern.ch/record/1165534/files/CERN-Brochure-2009-003-Eng.pdf"&gt;CERN reports the number of
collision per bunch to be about 20 for bunch size of
10&lt;/a&gt;^11^,
suggesting the cross-section of 60 mb used should be more like 4 mb.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's conventional to take the proton cross-section, which is dependent
on the proton energy but otherwise doesn't vary with the characteristics
of the accelerator, out of this equation; what's left is referred to as
the &lt;em&gt;luminosity&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ L = \frac{f n_I n_T }{\pi r^2}  $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is expressed in collisions per unit area per unit time, i.e. it
has units of [T]^-1^ [L]^-2^.  With luminosity so defined, the collision
rate is just the product of the accelerator's luminosity and the
cross-section of the proton collision (at the particular proton energy
in question).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total number of collisions during some time period is the integral
of the collision rate over the time period. Of course, this is equal to
the integral of the luminosity over the time period, times the
cross-section (assuming that the cross-section remains constant over
time, because it only depends on the beam energy, so it can be brought
out of this integration):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ N = \int_0^T R dt  $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$ N = \sigma \int_0^T L dt  $$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integrated luminosity has units of inverse area, [L]^-2^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unit of area in typical use is the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barn_%28unit%29"&gt;&lt;em&gt;barn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is
approximately the cross-sectional area of the
&lt;a href="http://education.jlab.org/itselemental/ele092.html"&gt;uranium&lt;/a&gt;nucleus (1
b is 10^-28^ m^2^). A &lt;em&gt;femtobarn&lt;/em&gt; is 10^-15^ b, so 1 fb = 10^-43^ m^2^.
Hence, the luminosity is measured in fb^-1^ s^-1^, which, when
multiplied by the collision cross-section in fb, gives a collision rate
in s^-1^. The time-integrated luminosity is therefore typically
expressed in &lt;em&gt;inverse femtobarns&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, the total number of
collisions is also usually quoted in inverse femtobarns (the true number
of collisions would be this number times the cross-section of the
proton-proton collision at whatever energy is being used). Given the
actual cross-section of the proton-proton collision at 7 TeV collision
energy, 1 fb^-1^ corresponds to about 8 × 10^12^ collisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What about the magnets?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several thousand superconducting magnets, cooled by helium to
1.9 K, of various types. For example, there are 392 quadrupole-type
magnets, which focus the proton beams along the straight sections, and
1,232 dipole magnets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So there were teething problems?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some early problems. On 27 March 2007 one of the
quadrupole-type superconducting magnets failed a preliminary test. The
magnet was deliberately being subjected to high pressures, similar to
those that occur during quenching. The magnet that failed was built by
Fermilab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was embarrassing, more for Fermilab than CERN, but things got worse
after initial switch-on. Protons were first streamed in both directions
around the tunnel on 10 September 2008, at 0.45 TeV beam energy.
However, only eight or nine days later, an accident occurred in which
the electrical connection between two of the 1,232 superconducting
dipole magnets evaporated while carrying a current of 8.7 kA, as the
beam energy was being increased to 5 TeV per beam. An electrical arc
occurred that ruptured the cooling system, allowing six tonnes of liquid
helium to boil off and leak into the tunnel. The pressure spike created
a shock wave that damaged a few hundred metres of the tunnel. Repairs
cost 40m Euros: 53 magnets had to be brought back to the surface, and
either repaired or replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 23 November 2009, over a year later, the LHC returned to accelerating
protons, initially at 0.45 TeV per beam again. On December 9 members of
the &lt;a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/1748-0221/3/08/S08003"&gt;ATLAS
collaboration&lt;/a&gt; spotted
2.36 TeV collisions during test circulations. By December 16, there had
been 50,000 collisions at this energy. Overall this was four years later
than originally expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2010, CERN announced its plans to keep the collision energy to
7 TeV for the next 18-24 months, or until an inverse femtobarn of data
had been collected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was realised that the copper stabilisers surrounding the
superconducting cables, which bear electrical current in the event that
the superconducting cables fail, had too high a resistance. There are
10,000 of these connections. The upgrade that has been going on over the
past two years has involved, among other things, replacing these shunts.
The upgrade cost 124m Euros. However, despite this, CERN is still going
to run LHC at 13 TeV rather than the design energy of 14 TeV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What are the experiments?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four interaction points around the ring. The two main
experiments are the 7000-tonne ATLAS and the 12,500-tonne CMS (compact
muon solenoid), which are general-purpose detectors involved in the
search for the Higgs boson. A third, smaller experiment -
&lt;a href="http://www-pnp.physics.ox.ac.uk/~lhcb/index.shtml"&gt;LHCb&lt;/a&gt; - is involved
in detailed investigations into B-mesons. A fourth is
&lt;a href="http://www.uslhc.us/What_is_the_LHC/Experiments/ALICE"&gt;ALICE&lt;/a&gt;, which is
designed to study collisions between nuclei such as lead, which the LHC
delivers in special runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is it for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Higgs boson was the last missing piece of &lt;a href="http://www.superstringtheory.com/experm/exper2.html"&gt;the Standard Model of
particle physics&lt;/a&gt;,
which was conceived in the early 1970s and remains the best description
of particle physics. The existence of the particle was predicted by
&lt;a href="http://www.ph.ed.ac.uk/higgs/peter-higgs"&gt;Peter Higgs&lt;/a&gt; in 1964, and
Higgs (along with&lt;a href="http://www.ulb.ac.be/sciences/physth/people_FEnglert.html"&gt;Francois
Englert&lt;/a&gt;) won
the &lt;a href="http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/2013/"&gt;Nobel Prize for physics in
2013&lt;/a&gt;,
after the particle was discovered at the LHC. The significance of the
Higgs is usually said to be that it explains how some particles acquire
mass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that there's a uniform scalar field pervading the universe,
and that interactions of particles with this field is what gives those
particles their mass. The stronger a particle's interaction with the
field is, the greater its mass. Photons have no interaction whatsoever,
electrons have a weak interaction, etc. This field has come to be known
as the &lt;a href="http://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Higgs_field"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Higgs field&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
and the phenomenon of particles acquiring mass through coupling with
this field as the &lt;em&gt;Higgs mechanism&lt;/em&gt;. An analogy often given for the
mechanism is that it's like the particles are travelling through treacle
or molasses; particles more strongly coupled to the field aren't able to
travel as far, before they decay into lighter particles. But Higgs
himself has complained that this isn't an appropriate metaphor, as the
mechanism isn't dissipative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mechanism was independently proposed by Francois Englert and
&lt;a href="http://cerncourier.com/cws/article/cern/46542"&gt;Robert Brout&lt;/a&gt; at the
&lt;a href="http://www.ulb.ac.be/ulb/presentation/uk.html"&gt;Free University of
Brussels&lt;/a&gt;, as well as
Higgs, and also by &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/04/us/gerald-guralnik-77-a-god-particle-pioneer-dies.html"&gt;Gerald
Guralnik&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.rochester.edu/news/hagen/"&gt;Carl Hagen&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/t.kibble"&gt;Thomas
Kibble&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="www.imperial.ac.uk"&gt;Imperial
College&lt;/a&gt;. Higgs has always felt uncomfortable about
his name being the one associated with the phenomenon; in fact, Brout
and Englert published their paper two weeks before he did. However,
Higgs was the one who proposed that the mechanism would have
'experimental consequences'; i.e. that, as a consequence of
wave-particle duality, vibrations in the Higgs field ought to manifest
as particles, in the same way that vibrations in the electromagnetic
field manifest as
&lt;a href="www.universetoday.com/74027/what-are-photons"&gt;photons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theory did not predict the mass, however, of the Higgs boson. Hence,
the &lt;a href="http://hepwww.rl.ac.uk/public/bigbang/file9.html"&gt;LEP&lt;/a&gt; (the Large
Electron Positron Collider, which previously occupied the tunnel the LHC
is in now and which operated with a collision energy of 200 GeV for 11
years from 1989 to 2000, to provide data to study the
&lt;a href="http://images-of-elements.com/particle-zoo/w-boson.php"&gt;W&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://images-of-elements.com/particle-zoo/z-boson.php"&gt;Z
bosons&lt;/a&gt;, as well
as to search for the Higgs boson), the &lt;a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-supercollider-that-never-was/"&gt;Superconducting Super
Collider&lt;/a&gt;
(which started to be built in Texas but was never completed due to cost
over-runs), the Tevatron at Fermilab, and ultimately the LHC, were
conceived of to verify the existence of the Higgs boson and measure its
mass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the LHC, theory suggested the mass of the Higgs was probably no
more than 186 GeV, and the LEP's failure to find it demonstrated that
the Higgs could not be less than 114 GeV. The Tevatron data at 1.96 TeV
collision energy ruled out masses around 165 GeV, and suggested the
160-180 GeV range was unlikely. This left two regions - a lighter region
of 114-160 GeV and a heavier region of 180-186 GeV - unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finding the Higgs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 30 March 2010, 18 months after start-up, the first collisions at 7
TeV collisions, were achieved, but at low luminosity. The original
intention was to run for 18-24 months at 7 TeV. Serious data collection
began in 2011; by summer 2011 the mass range of the Higgs had been
narrowed down to 115-145 GeV, and by 13 December 2011 CERN was able to
announce that the energy range had been restricted to 116-130 GeV, with
'an intriguing excess' at around 125 GeV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further measurements began in April 2012. At this point, the beam energy
was increased from 3.5 TeV to 4 TeV. On 4 July 2012, the discovery of
the Higgs boson, with a mass of around 125 GeV, was announced with
5&lt;span class="math"&gt;\( \sigma\)&lt;/span&gt; significance by both ATLAS and
&lt;a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/1748-0221/3/08/S08004/pdf/1748-0221_3_08_S08004.pdf"&gt;CMS&lt;/a&gt;.
This is the same mass as about 133 protons, or one caesium atom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A further three months of run time was announced beyond the scheduled
shut-down at the end of 2012. The first run ended in February 2013,
after three years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is 'five sigma' significance?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protons are collided in bunches, which causes pile-up - multiple
collisions within each bunch crossing. Furthermore, protons aren't
elementary particles like electrons, but are composite particles made of
&lt;a href="http://www.physics.ox.ac.uk/documents/PUS/dis/fundam.htm"&gt;quarks&lt;/a&gt;held
together by
&lt;a href="http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/ParticleAndNuclear/gluons.html"&gt;gluons&lt;/a&gt;.
Therefore, when they collide at these high energies, a lot of debris is
created - &lt;a href="www.feynman.com/"&gt;Feynman&lt;/a&gt;likened it to 'smashing garbage
cans into garbage cans'. This means there's a huge background of
detected events that disguise the events actually being looked for;
getting confidence about the signal in the light of this background
requires a very large number of collisions to be integrated over a long
period. This is why the luminosity is so significant; obviously the
higher the luminosity, the higher the collision rate, and the less time
it takes to accumulate the necessary data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the determination of the existence of the Higgs was a statistical
one, based on the agglomeration of a lot of data, rather than something
that could be determined from analysing any one particular collision.
There are many possible outcomes from a proton-proton collision at these
energies, each one a different combination of outgoing particles. Each
combination of outgoing particles is referred to as a &lt;em&gt;decay channel&lt;/em&gt;,
and the probability of each channel, and of the production of each
possible particle, is predicted by the Standard Model and precisely
known. Deviations from these known probabilities, indicating the
presence of a new particle, need to be built up over a long period of
time to establish confidence that it's not merely background. The number
of particles actually detected in a given energy range over a given
period of time is not fixed, but follows a &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/PoissonDistribution.html"&gt;Poisson
distribution&lt;/a&gt;
with a mean equal to the expected number based on the probability.
There's therefore a finite likelihood of detecting more than the
expected number even if there is no new particle in that energy range;
this is just a statistical fluctuation. The excess has to be large to be
attributed to the presence of a new particle; 5&lt;em&gt;σ&lt;/em&gt; is the 'gold
standard' (i.e. the excess has to be at least 5 times the standard
deviation for it to be confidently attributed to a new particle). An
excess of 3&lt;em&gt;σ&lt;/em&gt; is usually referred to as only 'evidence for' it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How much data is this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each collision/event that is recorded represents a few hundred MB of
data. Because only a small fraction of the theoretically-possible decay
channels involve a Higgs boson being produced, many can be disregarded;
hence only a small fraction of events taking place need to be recorded,
with the majority being deliberately discarded. The data is initially
stored at the on-site tape silo facility known as Tier 0. Reconstructed
data are delivered to regional centres around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upgrade involved:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgrading the 10,000 electrical interconnections between the dipole
    magnets (the component that failed in the accident that put the LHC
    out of commission for over a year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving the quench protection system, so that when quenching
    occurs the released energy is dissipated in a controlled way that
    minimises the chance of damage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replacing 18 of the 1,232 dipole magnets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgrading the cryogenics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving the vacuum in the beam pipe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These modifications will allow the LHC to operate safely at the higher
collision energy of 13 TeV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other operational change will be that the bunch size will be reduced
from 1.7 × 10^11^ protons per bunch down to 1.2 × 10^11^. This will
reduce 'pile-up', which is the simultaneous occurrence of numerous
collisions, which are hard to disentangle from each other when analysing
the data. However, the bunches will be collided every 25 ns instead of
every 50 ns, giving an overall increase in luminosity despite the
reduced bunch size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the two-year upgrade is complete, preparations are underway for the
next major run. The SPS - a 7 km-long accelerator that feeds protons to
the LHC - began being powered up in early July 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the next set of experiments are to further study the
Higgs, but also to investigate dark matter. We've known for some time
that observable matter and energy make up only 5% of the energy in the
universe; the rest is invisible, hard to detect, and we don't know what
it is. The remainder is comprised of &lt;em&gt;dark energy&lt;/em&gt; (70%) and &lt;em&gt;dark
matter&lt;/em&gt; (25%) - we know it's there only through its gravitational pull.
At the new high energies, LHC scientists hope to be able to detect
particles that display the same properties&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LHC is expected to operate into the 2030s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    var location_protocol = (false) ? 'https' : document.location.protocol;
    if (location_protocol !== 'http' &amp;&amp; location_protocol !== 'https') location_protocol = 'https:';
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = location_protocol + '//cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="particle physics"></category></entry></feed>